Guide to the Alan Tompkins works of art and papers ARCH162
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Alan Tompkins works of art and papers
1934-2007
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Tompkins, Alan
ARCH162
6.25 Linear Feet (27 containers)
The collection contains the artwork, papers, and photographs, of Alan Tompkins from 1934-2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Alan Tompkins was born in New Rochelle, NY on October 29, 1907 to Edward DeVoe Tompkins and Maude Peck. At an early age his father encouraged Tompkins artistic talents. By 1929, Tompkins graduated from Columbia University with a B.A. in history and art history. By 1933 he graduated with a B.F.A. degree from Yale Art School where he studied mural painting. Afterwards, he moved to Indianapolis and taught at the John Herron Art School. During the 1930s Tompkins won four national arts competitions and was awarded commissions to complete murals for the Works Progress Administration. By 1938, Tompkins had moved to Stratford, Connecticut and was working on book illustrations for a number of publishers while also teaching part-time at the Cooper Union Art School (and later Columbia, 1947-1951). From 1943 to 1947, Tompkins served as Design Supervisor for the General Electric Company. In 1951, Tompkins moved to Hartford to become the Assistant Director of the Hartford Art School. By 1957, he was the director of the art school as it merged with Hillyer College and the Hartt College of Music to become the University of Hartford, and was named the new university's Vice Chancellor of the Visual Arts. Tompkins continued as the director on the Hartford Art School until 1969, at which point he stepped down, but continued to teach as a professor at the school until 1974. After leaving the University, Tompkins continued to paint and exhibit his artwork. In August 2007, a solo exhibition of his works was held at the Silpe Gallery at the University of Hartford. Tompkins passed away on November 22, 2007. For more information on the life of Alan Tompkins, read "Alan Tompkins: Painter," by Linda P. Tomasso available in this collection and for circulation from Mortensen Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the artwork, papers, and photographs of Alan Tompkins during his career as an artist and teacher from the 1930s to 2007. Tompkins artwork in this collection consists of a wide variety of mediums including drawings, sketches, studies, as well as final versions of illustrations, prints, paintings, pastels, and watercolors. These works vary in style and subject matter. His papers consist primarily of his writings which consist of journal entries, notes, and his written thoughts on art and art education. His papers also include some lectures, speeches, research materials, publicity materials, correspondence, as well as items pertaining to his work and family history. The photographs in the collection are often of his artwork. These include photographs of works in progress in his studio and completed murals. However, there are also personal photographs of Tompkins and people who were close to him.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series: I. Works of Art, II. Papers, and III. Photographs.
Art, Modern -- 20th century; Art -- Study and teaching; Works of art; Photographs; Correspondence; diaries; Personal papers; Tompkins, Alan; University of Hartford. Hartford Art School
- Works of Art
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of drawings, sketches, pastels, paintings, and various other art mediums in a wide range of styles including portraits, landscapes, abstract works, and cubism.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by filename. Works that could be identified, including final works, sketches, and studies for that work, are filed by their title. The remaining artwork is filed by format or medium to the best of the processor's ability to distinguish them.
  - Bathers, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Book Cover Art, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Book Illustrations, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-14, Box 12, Folder 1-4)
  - Book Jacket Proofs, Circa 1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Books (Illustrated), 1945 - 1961 (Box 2)
  - Branchings, 1974 Sep 30 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Brick Panel of Hartford Hospital School of Nursing, 1966 Apr 22 (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Character, undated (Frame 0207303173968)
  - Christ Beckons Peter and Andrew, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Collages, undated (Box 12, Folder 5-7)
  - Connecticut Coin, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Contact Sport, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Country Road, undated (Frame 0207303173950)
  - Four Tips, 1969 Nov 5 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - G.E. Goblet Design, Circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Gloucester House, 1974 Dec 11 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Grid, 1974 Aug 4 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Harmonica Player, 1951 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Holy Family, 1952 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Incomplete Works, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Interior, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Island, 1952 (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Line Etude, undated (Frame 0207303173943)
  - Mansion, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Meig's Point, 1969 Sep 23 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Monhegan, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - To Mother with Love, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Nude in Forest, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Penwood, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 9-10)
  - Publication Illustrations, Circa 1950 - 1994 (Box 1, Folder 23-25, Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Red Banner, 1974 Oct 20 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Rock Landscape, 1974 Nov 5 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Self-Portraits, 1979; undated (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Sketch of Alan Topmkins, undated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbooks, 1987 Dec, undated (Box 1, Folder 26-30, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Folder 1-7, Box 13, Folder 9, Box 15)
  - Sketches, Studies, and Small Works (Box 5, Folder 8-13, Box 6, Box 7, Folder 1-5, Box 13, Folder 10-13)
  - Soldier, undated (Box 13, Folder 14)
  - Sunny Morning Sketch, 1933 (Box 18)
  - Trees, 1974 Aug 5 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Unidentified Drawings and Sketches (Box 14, Folder 3-4, Box 16, Folder 15-17, Box 18)
  - Unidentified Paintings (Box 7, Folder 6-7, Box 14, Folder 5-11, Box 17, Folder 1-5, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 23, Frame 0207303173935)
  - Unidentified Pastels (Box 14, Folder 12-14, Box 17, Folder 6-12, Box 22)
  - Unidentified Prints (Box 7, Folder 8-13, Box 14, Folder 15-16)
  - Unidentified Woodcut, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - University of Hartford Designs, Circa 1957 - 1999 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Untitled Portfolio of Connecticut Landmark Prints, undated (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - View, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - White Tree, Circa 1935 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Woman, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Works by Other Artists (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - X-mas Cards (Christmas Cards), 1946 - 1947, undated (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Papers
  The series consists of the personal papers of Alan Tompkins including his writings, correspondence, poetry, as well as publicity and research materials. The writing file makes up the majority of the series and consists of notes, lectures/speeches, and journal entries.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by filename.
  - Articles and Clippings (Box 7, Folder 18-19, Box 8, Folder 1-3, Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Awards and Certificates (Box 8, Folder 4, Box 14, Folder 20, Box 15)
  - Books (Box 2, Box 15)
  - Brochures, 1963, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1960 - 2005, undated (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
  - Exhibitions, 1954-1984 (Box 8, Folder 8-11, Box 15)
  - General Electric Kitchen Cabinets Patent, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - John F. Kennedy Envelope and Stamp, 1964 May 29 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Lectures by Others, 1954 - 1968 (Box 8, Folder 14-15)
  - List of Artwork, Circa 1941 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Poetry, 1975-1993, undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Publicity (Box 8, Folder 18, Box 9, Folder 1, Box 19, Folder 21-22)
  - Tompkins Family, 1891 - 2000 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - University of Hartford, Hartford Art School Bulletins, 1963; 1968 (Box 15)
  - West Hartford Art League (WHAL), 1997 (Box 9, Folder 3-4)
  - Writings, 1936 - 2006, undated (Box 9, Folder 5-21, Box 10, Folder 1-5, Box 14, Folder 23)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series consists mostly of depictions of his artwork in progress and once completed. There are also photographs of Alan Tompkins and others in the personal photographs files in this series.
  The photographs series is arranged alphabetically by filename.
  - Artist's Mother, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Bathers, undated (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Boone, NC Mural, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Brick Wall at Hartford Hospital School of Nursing, 1966 Mar (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - College Board Medal, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Columbia University Club Roof Garden Mural, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - The Dinner, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Domestic Tragedy, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Faculty Club Dining Room, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Gallery on the Green, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - General Electric Designs, 1945 - 1946 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Hitchhiker, undated (Box 10, Folder 17-18)
  - House-Raising Bee in West Hartford, 1790, undated (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Indiana Farm Sunday Afternoon, 1938 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Infirmary - General Electric Company Mural, 1944 (Box 10, Folder 21-22, Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Lake Landscape, undated (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Letter Carrier, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Living Room Panels, undated (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - Marian Anderson Mural Competition Sketch, 1941 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Mohegan, 1963 Dec (Box 10, Folder 27)
  - No Smoking, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 28)
  - Personal Photographs, 1934-1982 (Box 10, Folder 29-31, Box 14, Folder 1, Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Picnic, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 32)
  - Portrait of George Gates Roddin, 1942 (Box 10, Folder 33)
  - Portrait of Mrs. Andrew Seyer, 1946 Jun (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Portrait of Mrs. Turchik of Bridgeport, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 35)
  - Receiving News, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 36)
  - Self-Portrait, 1933, 1947 (Box 10, Folder 37-38)
  - Sun Bathers, undated (Box 10, Folder 39)
  - Sunny Morning, 1933 (Box 10, Folder 40)
  - Tan Still Life, undated (Box 10, Folder 41)
  - Tobacco Farming, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Unidentified Bathers, undated (Box 10, Folder 43)
  - Unidentified Color Study, undated (Box 10, Folder 44)
  - Unidentified Display, undated (Box 10, Folder 45)
  - Unidentified Life Painting, undated (Box 10, Folder 46)
  - Unidentified Mural at Post Office, undated (Box 10, Folder 47)
  - Unidentified Mural Outside, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified Nude Study, undated (Box 10, Folder 48)
  - Unidentified Paintings, Drawings, and Sketches, 1940-1959, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Unidentified Portraits, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Unidentified Sculpture, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified Still Life, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - War Thoughts, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - World War II Soldier, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)